What I want to talk to you about today is
ما أود التحدث عنه اليوم هو
virtual worlds, digital globes, the 3-D Web, the Metaverse.
العوالم الإفتراضية، الكواكب الرقمية، الشبكة ثلاثية الأبعاد، الكون الفوقي
What does this all mean for us?
ماذا يعني ذلك لنا؟
What it means is the Web is going to become an exciting place again.
ما يعنيه هو أن الشبكة ستصبح مجددا مكانا مثيرا
It's going to become super exciting as we transform
ستصبح مثيرة جدا بينما نتحول
to this highly immersive and interactive world.
إلى هذا العالم الغامر التفاعلي
With graphics, computing power, low latencies,
برسومات، قوة حسابية، وتفاعل سريع
these types of applications and possibilities
مثل هذه التطبيقات والإمكانات
are going to stream rich data into your lives.
ستدفق بيانات غنية إلى حياتنا
So the Virtual Earth initiative, and other types of these initiatives,
فمبادرة الأرض الإفتراضية، وغيرها من المبادرات المماثلة
are all about extending our current search metaphor.
جميعها متعلقة بتوسيع، كما تعلمون، طريقتنا الحالية للبحث
When you think about it, we're so constrained by browsing the Web,
حين تفكرون في الأمر، فنحن مقيدون جدا في تصفحنا للشبكة
remembering URLs, saving favorites.
تذكر الروابط، وحفظ المواقع
As we move to search, we rely on the relevance rankings,
بينما نتحرك للبحث، فنحن نعتمد في الحقيقة على تصنيف العلاقات
the Web matching, the index crawling.
مطابقة الشبكة، والمؤشرات الزاحفة
But we want to use our brain!
ولكننا نود إستخدام عقولنا
We want to navigate, explore, discover information.
نود أن تبحر، ونستكشف، ونكتشف المعلومات
In order to do that, we have to put you as a user back in the driver's seat.
ولكي نتمكن من ذلك، يجب علينا إعادة المستخدم إلى مقعد القيادة
We need cooperation between you and the computing network and the computer.
نحتاج إلى تعاون بينك وبين شبكة الحاسب والحاسب
So what better way to put you back in the driver's seat
وهل من طريقة أفضل لإعادتك في مقعد القيادة
than to put you in the real world that you interact in every day?
من إعادتك إلى العالم الحقيقي الذي تتفاعل معه كل يوم
Why not leverage the learnings that you've been learning your entire life?
لماذا لا نستفيد من خبراتك التي كونتها طوال حياتك؟
So Virtual Earth is about starting off
فالأرض الإفتراضية هي، كما تعلمون، بداية
creating the first digital representation, comprehensive, of the entire world.
صنع أول تمثيل رقمي، شامل، للعالم أجمع
What we want to do is mix in all types of data.
ما نود فعله هو خلط جميع أنواع البيانات
Tag it. Attribute it. Metadata. Get the community to add local depth,
ترميزها، وتصنيفها. وتمكين المجتمع من إضافة العمق المحلي
global perspective, local knowledge.
والمنظور العالمي، والمعارف المحلية
So when you think about this problem,
فحين تفكر في هذه المشكلة
what an enormous undertaking. Where do you begin?
أي جهود ضخمة. تعلمون، أين تبدأ؟
Well, we collect data from satellites, from airplanes,
لذا، جمعنا البيانات من الأقمار الصناعية، من الطائرات
from ground vehicles, from people.
من المركبات البرية، من الناس
This process is an engineering problem,
العملية، كما تعلمون، هي مشكلة هندسية
a mechanical problem, a logistical problem, an operational problem.
مشكلة ميكانيكية، مشكلة منطقية، ومشكلة تنفيذية
Here is an example of our aerial camera.
هذا مثال لكمرتنا الجوية
This is panchromatic. It's actually four color cones.
هذه ملونة. إنها في الواقع أربعة مخروطات ملونة
In addition, it's multi-spectral.
إضافة إلى كونها متعددة الأطياف
We collect four gigabits per second of data,
نجمع أربع جيجا بت من البيانات في الثانية
if you can imagine that kind of data stream coming down.
إذا تخيلتم تدفق البيانات
That's equivalent to a constellation of 12 satellites at highest res capacity.
هذا يعادل مجموعة من 12 قمر صناعي على أقصى طاقة
We fly these airplanes at 5,000 feet in the air.
نطير بهذه الطائرات على إرتفاع 5,000 قدم
You can see the camera on the front. We collect multiple viewpoints,
يمكنكم رؤية الكميرا في المقدمة. نحن نجمع عدة زوايا
vantage points, angles, textures. We bring all that data back in.
وجهات النظر، زوايا، وأنسجة. نعود بكل هذه البيانات
We sit here -- you know, think about the ground vehicles, the human scale --
نجلس هنا -- كما تعلمون، المركبات الأرضية، والمقياس البشري -ـ
what do you see in person? We need to capture that up close
ما الذي تراه بعينيك؟ نحتاج أن نلتقط ذلك عن قرب
to establish that what it's like-type experience.
لتكون الخبرة أكثر واقعية
I bet many of you have seen the Apple commercials,
أنا متأكد أن أكثركم قد شاهد إعلانات آبل
kind of poking at the PC for their brilliance and simplicity.
الذي ينغز في الحاسب لذكائهم وبساطتهم
So a little unknown secret is --
سأشارككم سر صغير
did you see the one with the guy, he's got the Web cam?
هل رأيتم الرجل الذي يحمل الكاميرا
The poor PC guy. They're duct taping his head. They're just wrapping it on him.
رجل الحاسب المسكين، إنهم يربطون رأسه باللاصق
Well, a little unknown secret is his brother actually works on the Virtual Earth team.
من الأسرار غير المعروفه أن أخاه في الواقع يعمل مع فريق الأرض الإفتراضية
(Laughter). So they've got a little bit of a sibling rivalry thing going on here.
(ضحك). بينهم القليل من التنافس الأخوي
But let me tell you -- it doesn't affect his day job.
ولكن دعوني أخبركم -- أنها لا تؤثر على عمله اليومي
We think a lot of good can come from this technology.
نعتقد أن الكثير من النافع يمكن أن تنتج من هذه التقنية
This was after Katrina. We were the first commercial fleet of airplanes
كان هذا بعد كترينا. كنا أول أسطول تجاري من الطائرات
to be cleared into the disaster impact zone.
يسمح له الدخول إلى منطقة الكارثة
We flew the area. We imaged it. We sent in people. We took pictures of interiors,
حلقنا في المنطقة، صورناها، أرسلنا أناس، صورناها من داخل
disaster areas. We helped with the first responders, the search and rescue.
مناطق الكوارث. ساعدنا في البحث والإنقاذ
Often the first time anyone saw what happened to their house was on Virtual Earth.
في كثير من الأحيان كان أول ما يرون ما حدث لمنازلهم كان في الأرض الإفتراضية
We made it all freely available on the Web, just to --
وفرناها مجانا على الشبكة، فقط -- كما تعلمون
it was obviously our chance of helping out with the cause.
كانت فرصتنا لنساعد في القضية
When we think about how all this comes together,
حين نفكر في الأمر، كما تعلمون، كيف نجمع هذا كله
it's all about software, algorithms and math.
الأمر متعلق بالبرمجيات، الخوارزميات والرياضيات
You know, we capture this imagery but to build the 3-D models
هل تعلمون، نلتقط هذه الصور، ولكن لبناء نموذج ثلاثي الأبعاد
we need to do geo-positioning. We need to do geo-registering of the images.
نحتاج إلى تحديد الموقع الجغرافي، والتسجيل الجغرافي للصور
We have to bundle adjust them. Find tie points.
نحتاج إلى تكييفها في حزم. العثور على نقاط ربط
Extract geometry from the images.
إستخلاص الأبعاد من الصور
This process is a very calculated process.
هذه عملية محسوبة بدقة
In fact, it was always done manual.
في الواقع، كانت دائما ما تفعل يدويا
Hollywood would spend millions of dollars to do a small urban corridor
هوليوود ستصرف الملايين من الدولارات لصنع ممر صغير
for a movie because they'd have to do it manually.
لفلم لأنهم سيضطرون إلى صنعه يدويا
They'd drive the streets with lasers called LIDAR.
سيجوبون الشوارع بليزر
They'd collected information with photos. They'd manually build each building.
سيجمعون المعلومات مع الصور، ويقومون ببناء كل مبنى يدويا
We do this all through software, algorithms and math --
نقوم نحن بكل ذلك عبر البرمجيات، الخوارزميات والرياضيات
a highly automated pipeline creating these cities.
عملية آلية تماما لصنع هذه المدن
We took a decimal point off what it cost to build these cities,
لقد أزلنا فاصلة عشرية من ما تكلفه صناعة هذه المدن
and that's how we're going to be able to scale this out and make this reality a dream.
وهذا ما سيمكننا من التوسع وجعل هذا الحلم حقيقة
We think about the user interface.
نفكر في واجهة المستخدم
What does it mean to look at it from multiple perspectives?
ما الذي يعنيه النظر من عدة وجهات
An ortho-view, a nadir-view. How do you keep the precision of the fidelity of the imagery
كيف يمكن الحفاظ على دقة وصحة الصور
while maintaining the fluidity of the model?
بينما نحافظ على سلاسة النموذج
I'll wrap up by showing you the --
سأختتم بهذا العرض
this is a brand-new peek I haven't really shown into the lab area of Virtual Earth.
هذه نظرة جديدة لم تظهر في مختبرات الأرض الإفتراضية
What we're doing is -- people like this a lot,
ما نفعله هو -- الناس يحبون هذا كثيرا -ـ
this bird's eye imagery we work with. It's this high resolution data.
هذه صور التحليق التي نعمل بها. إنها هذه البيانات عالية الدقة
But what we've found is they like the fluidity of the 3-D model.
ولكن ما وجدناه أنهم حبون سلاسة النموذج الثلاثي الأبعاد
A child can navigate with an Xbox controller or a game controller.
يمكن لطفل أن يبحر بيد التحكم
So here what we're trying to do is we bring the picture and project it into the 3-D model space.
فما نحاول فعله هنا هو أخذ الصور وبثها في النموذج ثلاثي الأبعاد
You can see all types of resolution. From here, I can slowly pan the image over.
يمكنكم رؤية جميع أنواع الدقة. من هنا، يمكنني سحب الصورة
I can get the next image. I can blend and transition.
يمكنني الحصول على الصورة التالية. يمكنني المزج والإنتقال
By doing this I don't lose the original detail. In fact, I might be recording history.
بالقيام بذلك، لا أفقد البيانات الأصلية. في الواقع، قد أسجل التاريخ
The freshness, the capacity. I can turn this image.
النضارة، المساحة. يمكنني إدارة هذه الصورة
I can look at it from multiple viewpoints and angles.
يمكنني النظر إليها من عدة وجهات وزوايا
What we're trying to do is build a virtual world.
ما نحاول فعله هو بناء علم إفتراضي
We hope that we can make computing a user model you're familiar with,
نأمل أن نتمكن من جعل الحاسب نموذجا مألوف لكم
and really derive insights from you, from all different directions.
وفعلا استخلاص رؤى منكم، من جميع الاتجاهات مختلفة
I thank you very much for your time.
شكرا جزيلا على وقتكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)